<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>

<!-- Expand crefs and put them inline -->
<?rfc comments='yes' ?>
<?rfc inline='yes' ?>

<rfc category="std"
     docName="draft-hinden-6man-ipv6-edge-subnet-00.txt"
     ipr="trust200902">

<front>
    <title abbrev="Simple CLAT in Edge">
      Simple CLAT Deployment in IPv6 Edge Subnets
    </title>

   <author fullname="Robert M. Hinden" initials="R." surname="Hinden">
     <organization>Check Point Software</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>959 Skyway Road</street>
          <city>San Carlos</city>
          <code>94070</code>
          <region>CA</region>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>bob.hinden@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

   <author fullname="Christian Huitema" initials="C." surname="Huitema">
      <organization>Private Octopus Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street> </street>
          <city>Friday Harbor</city>
          <code>98250</code>
          <region>WA</region>
          <country>U.S.A.</country>
        </postal>
        <email>huitema@huitema.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2017" />

    <abstract>
        <t>
The 464XLAT strategy for ensuring IPv4 connectivity through IPv6 only provider
networks relies on deployment of CLAT functions in edge networks. These
functions requires assignment of a specific IPv6 prefix. We propose
a simple way to deploy the CLAT function in edge networks while only
requiring a single /64 prefix for the IPv6 edge network. The CLAT prefix
will be self-assigned from this prefix, without requiring explicit
provisioning by the network provider.
        </t>
    </abstract>
</front>

<middle>
<section title="Introduction" anchor="intro" >
<t>
The 464XLAT strategy is defined in <xref target="RFC6877"/>. It ensures
ensuring IPv4 connectivity through IPv6 only provider
networks by deployment of IPv4 to IPv6 CLAT functions in edge networks,
and IPv6 to IPv4 PLAT functions in provider networks. Each CLAT deployment
requires assignment of a specific IPv6 prefix. 
</t>
<t>
The standard practice in edge networks is to use the prefix delegation mechanism
and obtain a single /64 network prefix from the network service provider. The
CLAT deployment would in theory require an additional prefix for each network.
This increases the number of prefixes required for network operation, and 
generally introduces friction in the deployment of CLAT functions.
</t>
<t>
In this document, we propose an alternative in which the CLAT functions
self assign a /96 prefix inside the /64 prefix assigned to the home network.
</t>
 

<section title="Terminology" anchor="terminology">
  

<t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
   NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
   "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in
   RFC 2119 <xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
</section>

</section> <!-- end of introduction -->


<section title="464XLAT and CLAT deployment" anchor="problem" >
<t>
The 464XLAT transition mechanism define in <xref target="RFC6877"/>
relies on two successive translations:
<list style="numbers">
<t>
The packet originates in an edge network as IPv4, and is routed to the default
IPv4 router for the network, which implements a CLAT function.
</t>
<t>
The CLAT translates the packet from IPv4 to IPv6 according to <xref target="RFC6145"/>
The source IPv4 address
is obtained by combining the original IPv4 source address with the local
CLAT prefix. The destination IPv6 address is obtained by combining
the original IPv4 source address with the PLAT prefix.
</t>
<t>
The packet is routed over IPv6 to the PLAT.
</t>
<t>
The PLAT translates the packet from IPv6 to IPv4 according to <xref target="RFC6146"/>.
</t>
<t>
The packet is routed to the IPv4 destination.
</t>
</list>
The reverse translations are performed in the opposite direction.
</t>
<t>
The construction of the prefixes for IPv6/IPv4 address translators is specified in
<xref target="RFC6052"/>, which allows multiple prefix sizes. In what follows,
we will assume that the CLAT prefix is a /96.
</t>
<t>
The simple deployment makes a set of assumptions:
<list style="symbols">
<t>
The edge network advertises a /64 prefix for
IPv6 Stateless Address Autoconfiguration according to 
<xref target="RFC4862"/>.
</t>
<t>
The CLAT function is configured with the 
prefix of the preferred PLAT.
</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

<section title="Self assigned subnet" >
<t>
The first step is configuration of the CLAT is the configuration of an IPv6 /96 CLAT
prefix. The prefix MUST BE configured by concatenating:
<list style="symbols">
<t>
The /64 prefix of the local network.
</t>
<t>
A random 16 bit CLAT subnet number.
</t>
<t>
A 16 bit number chosen so that the /96 prefix is "checksum neutral" according
to <xref target="RFC6145"/>.
</t>
</list>
The prefix is only valid as long as the /64 prefix of the local network is valid.
Similarly to what is explained in <xref target="RFC4862"/>, the /96 bit
prefix MUST NOT be used if the /64 bit prefix is no longer valid.
</t>


</section> <!-- end of Self assigned subnet -->

<section title="Defending a subnet claim with DAD">
<t>
TO DO: how to use DAD to claim a /80 or a /96.
</t>
<t>
TO DO: probabilies of SLAAC collision with a self assigned subnet. 
Show that this is typically not very large.
</t>
</section> <!-- end of DAD -->

<section title="Routing considerations" >
<t>
TODO: general solution using ND proxy.
</t>
<t>
TODO: what about multicast.
</t>
<t>
TODO: special case of same box colocation. The home router also manages the special purpose network.
Example are dedicated Wi-Fi network with special password, or CLAT managed by edge router.
</t>

</section> <!-- end of routing -->

<section title="Security Considerations" anchor="securityCons" >
<t>
Yeah, right.
</t>

</section> <!-- end of security -->


<section title="IANA Considerations" anchor="iana">
<t>
This draft does not require any IANA action.
</t>
</section> <!-- end of iana -->

<section title="Acknowledgments">
<t>
We would like to thank the 6MAN working member for the long and constructive discussion that motivated this draft.
</t>
</section>
</middle>

<back>

<references title="Normative References">

	<?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119" ?>

	<?rfc include="reference.RFC.6877" ?>

	<?rfc include="reference.RFC.6145" ?>

	<?rfc include="reference.RFC.6146" ?>

	<?rfc include="reference.RFC.6052" ?>

	<?rfc include="reference.RFC.4862" ?>

</references>
</back>
</rfc>
